Guide to the Gertrud Lackschewitz Papers 1839-2008 (bulk 1890-1984)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Gertrud Lackschewitz papers
1839-2008 (bulk 1890-1984)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 827
Lackschewitz, Gertrud b. 1923
6.1 linear feet and 42 audiocassettes
Gertud Lackschewitz was a professor of German Language and Literature at the University of Montana from 1960 until 1989. This collection primarily consists of research files related to her work with German immigrants and individuals of German ancestry in Montana.
Many of the items in the research files of this collection are copies of originals housed at the Montana Historical Society, in Helena, Montana. Items have the collection title and number attached to them for reference. The collection also contains microfilm from the University of Chicago.
Biographical Note
Gertrud Degenhard was born in March of 1923 in Gelsenkirchen, Germany. The second child of six, Gertrud’s early life was colored by the social and economic strife afflicting post-war Germany. Originally pursuing a degree in medicine, she studied in Berlin during World War II and often had to endure allied air raids interrupting lectures. She switched to the humanities, delving into history, literature, philosophy, art history, and language. In 1944, she was drafted into military service and served as a map clerk with the German Special Forces. After the war, she completed her exams and was certified as a high school teacher. She continued with her studies and earned her doctorate at Goettingen University in History and Germanistics before joining her fiancée, Klaus Lackschewitz, in the United States in 1954.
Gertrud and Klaus were married shortly after her arrival in the United States. They lived on farms in both New Jersey and Virginia for a time. They then moved to New York City where Klaus worked as a gardener and Gertrud as a cook, while Gertrud tried to improve their position by taking classes at the Columbia University Teacher’s College and improving her English. Klaus continued to take gardening jobs and Gertrud eventually got a position at the Teacher’s College Library as a clerk. She worked as a clerk for a year before she took a job as a reference librarian with the New York Public Library. Victim of the policies of the time, she was fired when she reached her fifth month of her first pregnancy in 1959. She gained the director of the library’s help in finding a grant that allowed her to continue working through the pregnancy. She wrote a bibliography on the history of interior decoration, which she worked on until a week before her daughter Anna’s birth and returned to a week after the delivery. However, she did lose her reference position and after she completed the bibliography she was out of a job.
Gertrud took a position with Montana State University (now the University of Montana) in Missoula, Montana, as an assistant professor of German in the fall of 1960. She also had a second daughter, Elizabeth, after moving to Missoula. Lackschewitz initially only taught German language courses, but as she worked her way from assistant to associate to full professor she also taught literature courses. Through her teaching and interaction with students, she noticed that many had German ancestry. As a German immigrant and instructor of German, she was intrigued by these students’ background and began a research project that delved into German immigration to Montana. Through her extensive research, she devised several chapters for a book about German immigrants in Montana based on Helena Germans, Russian Germans, Hutterites, and German churches. However, after she retired from teaching in 1989, she never completed the book.
Klaus Lackschewitz passed away on August 10, 1995. Gertrud continues to live in Missoula, Montana.
The collection is primarily Gertrud Lackschewitz’s research files and recorded interviews relating to German immigration. Her research includes articles, books, bibliographies, notes, photographs, maps, prints, advertisements, announcements, pamphlets, newspapers, card files, and questionnaires relating to German immigrant settlements, religion, language, education, music, poetry, and livelihood in Montana and the United States. Card files and notes in many of the Montana research files relate directly to the taped interviews. The collection contains extensive research on Hutterite colonies in Montana, especially Hutterite religion and culture in Montana and Canada. Also included are Lackschewitz’s own writings and lectures on German immigrants as well as a memoir which includes her own story but also memories set down by her husband, Klaus; material relating to national and local events for the tricentennial of German immigration to the United States; and personal correspondence with friends and colleagues.
The collection is arranged into eight series, one of which has been further arranged in subseries. The contents of each series or subseries are arranged chronologically.
Series I: Research Files, 1.7 linear feet and 42 audiocassettes, 1863-1999
Subseries 1: German Immigrants in Montana, 1.1 linear feet, 1863-1984
Subseries 2: German Language Churches in Montana, 0.6 linear feet, 1910-1999
Subseries 3: Audio Recordings, 42 audiocassettes, 1972-1984
Series II: Writings and Lectures, 0.4 linear feet, 1979-2006
Subseries 1: Writings and Lectures, 0.3 linear feet, 1979-1984 and undated
Subseries 2: Memoirs, 0.1 linear feet, 2006
Series III: Correspondence, 0.2 linear feet, 1979-2008
Series IV: German-American Tricentennial, 0.2 linear feet, 1982-1983
Series V: Card Files, 1.7 linear feet, circa 1965-1985
Series VI: German Immigrants in the United States Research Files, 1.0 linear foot, 1839-1984
Series VII: Germans in Europe, 0.3 linear feet, 1864-1983
Series VIII: Photographs, 1.0 linear foot, 1896-1936
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
These materials were compiled and held by Gertrud Lackschewitz until their donation to Archives and Special Collections in 2011.
This collection was donated by the creator, Gertrud Lackschewitz, to the University of Montana Archives and Special Collections in 2011.
A collection of diaries, ledgers, notebooks, and letters created by August Hollensteiner were removed from the collection during processing and arranged into its own separate collection, the August Hollensteiner Papers, Mss 829. Lackschewitz collected the Hollensteiner items as source material for her work on German immigrants in Montana.
The University of Montana Archives and Special Collections also holds two oral histories of Gertrud Lackschewitz, OH 434, which are available online.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana--Church history; Montana--Emigration and immigration; Montana--Genealogy
German Americans--Montana; Immigrants--Montana
Sound Recordings; Interviews--Montana--Missoula County; Interviews--Montana--Missoula County
Colleges and Universities; German Americans; Montana; Religion
Women college teachers--Montana--Missoula County
- Research Files, 1863-1999; Series I; 1.7 linear feet and 42 audiocassettes
  - German Immigrants in Montana, 1863-1984; Subseries 1; 1.1 linear feet
    - Reinig Family, Helena, Montana, 1863-1981 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Lambert Naegele, Helena, Montana, 1875-1984 and undated (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Singing Groups, 1881-1910 and undated (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Burlington Northern, 1883-1982 and undated (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Conrad Kohrs, 1885-1917 and undated (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Clippings, 1886-1909 and undated (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Census Records, 1890-1930 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Staats-Zeitung, German Language Newspaper, March 24, 1894 (Folder OS 16)
    - Concert Programs, 1894-1899 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Helena, Montana, 1894-1984 and undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Order of the Sons of Hermann, 1896-1942 and undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Program Advertisements, 1910 and undated (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Staats-Zeitung, German Language Newspaper, circa 1911 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Montana Council of Defense, 1918-1919 and undated (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Erinnerung an den Tag der Konfirmation, "Commemoration of the Day of Confirmation, July 1930 (Folder OS 16)
    - Great Western Sugar Company, 1934-1982 and undated (Box-folder 1/14)
    - German Language Newspapers, 1935-1979 and undated (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Chinook, Montana and Havre, Montana, 1953-1972 and undated (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Butte, Montana, 1953-1984 and undated (Box-folder 1/17)
    - “Foreign Born Population in Montana, 1870-1900”, 1956 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - "Protestantism in Early Frontier America, 1860-1925" - microfilm, 1963 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Fred Kuphal, Helena, Montana, 1967-1975 and undated (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Annual Herbstfest in Laurel Montana, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Helena, Montana Architecture, 1976-1981 and undated (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Helmville, Montana and Ovando, Montana, 1981-1984 and undated (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Herman Michael Family History, 1982-1984 and undated (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Hans Luthye Interview, Philipsburg, Montana, 1984 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Arthur Seiler, Helena, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Billings, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Dawson County, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
    - German and Scandinavian Pioneers, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
    - German Language, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    - "The Gluckstal Connection: Protestant Black Sea Russian-Germans in Montana and the Dakotas" (Restricted - Student Paper), undated; (Restricted - Student Paper) (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Immigration Maps, undated (Box-folder 2/13)
    - John Adami, Helena, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
    - John Wendel, Helena, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Laurel, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Memoirs, Great Falls, Montana and Big Timber, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Missoula, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Montana Historical Society Research, undated (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Nickolas Kessler, Helena, Montana, undated (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Plentywood, Montana, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Questionnaires and Research, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Theodore Kleinschmidt, Helena, Montana, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - German Language Churches in Montana, 1910-1999; Subseries 2; 0.6 linear feet
    - Lutheran Churches, Sheridan County, Montana, 1910-1940 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Zion Church, Watkins, Montana, 1913-1957 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Mennonites, 1915-1983 and undated (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Congregational-Christian Year-Book, 1918-1930 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Missouri Synod, 1935-1984 and undated (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Evangelical Churches, 1939-1982 and undated (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Lutheran Churches, 1939-1983 and undated (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Bethel Baptist Church, Missoula, Montana, 1957-1980 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - First Congregational Church, Laurel, Montana, 1957-1984 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - German Congregations, General, 1959-1983 and undated (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Father Eberschweiler, German Jesuit Missionary, 1960-1981 and undated (Box-folder 3/14)
    - St. John's Lutheran Church, Laurel, Montana, 1963 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Mennonites in the Flathead Valley, Montana, 1963-1984 and undated (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Brotherhood, Cogregational Church, 1964-1976 and undated (Box-folder 4/2)
    - German-Catholic Missions, 1967 and undated (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Trinity Lutheran Church, Missouri Synod, Billings, Montana, 1977-1981 and undated (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Hutterites, 1978-2002 and undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - First Lutheran Church, Bozeman, Montana, 1979-1981 and undated (Box-folder 4/6)
    - "Churches' Role in the Retention and Assimilation of German Culture: A Case Study of the Bethel Baptist and First Lutheran church in Missoula, Montana (Restricted - Student Paper), 1981; (Restricted - Student Paper) (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Trinity Lutheran Church, Great Falls, Montana, 1981-1982 and undated (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Lutheran Church, Helena, Montana, 1983 and undated (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Hutterite Gildford Colony Gazette, September 1998-February 1999 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - German Background Churches in Montana, 1900-1930, Map, undated (Folder OS 16)
    - German Background Churches in Montana, 1900-1930, Map, undated (Folder OS 16)
  - Audio Recordings, 1972-1984; Subseries 3; 42 audiocassettes
    This subseries consists of audio cassettes of interviews with individuals and some music. Most of the interviews were conducted in English, but several of them were conducted in German, or a combination of German and English.
    In 2019, the audio interviews were assigned an oral history collection name, German Immigrants in Montana Oral History Project and given collection number OH 433 to facilitate discovery and access.
    Electronic copies of the interviews are available from the University of Montana's Archives and Special Collections as oral history project OH 433.
    - Alese Dortman, music, undated (Cassette Cassette 1)
    - Henry and Olga Ostwald interview, Laurel, Montana, 1972 (Cassette Cassette 1)
    - Herman and Amelia Michael interview, Laurel, Montana, September 1980 (Cassette Cassette 2)
    - Henry and Mollie Gomer and Herman and Amelia Michael interview, Laurel, Montana, September 27, 1980 (Cassette Cassette 3)
    - Gottfried and Ottilia Schmidt interview, Fallon, Montana, circa 1980; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 4)
    - Daniel Schlenker interview, Terry, Montana, circa 1980; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 4)
    - Maria Maier interview, Circle, Montana, September 17, 1980; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 4)
    - Ishmael "Babe" Yost interview, Billings, Montana, 1981; Interview conducted in English and German. (Cassette Cassette 5)
    - Ishmael "Babe" Yost interview, Billings, Montana, September 1982; Interview conducted in English and German. (Cassette Cassette 6)
    - Reverend Paul Freiburger interview, Billings, Montana, 1981 (Cassette Cassette 7)
    - Julie Kober interview, Billings, Montana, 1981; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 7)
    - Hollensteiner family interview, June 1981; Interview with children or grandchildren of August Hollensteiner. (Cassette Cassette 8)
    - Erna Krueg Wenz interview, Baker, Montana, June 30, 1981 (Cassette Cassette 9)
    - Katherine Miller interview, Baker, Montana, June 30, 1981 (Cassette Cassette 9)
    - Louise Bauer interview, Havre, Montana, June 21, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 10)
    - Reverend Fred Schneider interview, Billings, Montana, July 3, 1981; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 11)
    - Sylvia Friedrich and Anna Rehner interview, Plentywood, Montana, August 1981 (Cassette Cassette 12)
    - John and Harriet Magstadt interview, Missoula, Montana, March 1982 (Cassette Cassette 13)
    - Kathryn Bertsch Staiger interview, Missoula, Montana, February 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 14)
    - Reverend Dale Erbele interview, South Hills Evangelical Church, Missoula, Montana, February 1982 (Cassette Cassette 14)
    - Julia Heinle and Kathy Oelke interview, Missoula, Montana, February 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. Oelke serves as Heinle's translator. (Cassette Cassette 14)
    - Hilda Vetter interview, April 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 15)
    - Reverend David Graff interview, Missoula, Montana, April 1982 (Cassette Cassette 15)
    - Sarah Stahl and family interview and songs, Gildford Hutterite Colony, Montana, June 21, 1982; Interview conducted in German. Songs sung in German. (Cassette Cassette 16)
    - Roland Toews interview, Lustre, Montana, June 30, 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 17)
    - Paul Koslowski interview, Wolf Point, Montana, July 1, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 17)
    - Jakab "Jake" Lackmann interview, Hardin, Montana, August 17, 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 18)
    - Georg Schreiner interview, Laurel, Montana, August 23, 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 19)
    - Fred Feuerbacher interview, Laurel, Montana, August 23, 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 19)
    - Wilhelmine Frank interview, Laurel, Montana, August 25, 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 20)
    - Herman Michael interview, Laurel, Montana, August 25, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 20)
    - Esther Wilhelm interview, Laurel, Montana, August 25, 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 21)
    - Pastor Elmer Wilhelm interview, First Congregational Church, Laurel, Montana, August 26, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 21)
    - Henry and Mollie Gomer interview, Laurel, Montana, August 26, 1982; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 22)
    - Laura Preizkas interview, Laurel, Montana, August 28, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 23)
    - Pastor Herb Schaal interview, Pilgrim Congregational Church, Billings, Montana, September 1982 (Cassette Cassette 24)
      Interview conducted in German and English.
    - Heinrich "Henry" Reiter interview, Laurel, Montana, September 11, 1982 (Cassette Cassette 25)
    - Jacob "Jake" Marker interview, Billings, Montana, September 13, 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 25)
    - Augusta Seidel interview, Great Falls, Montana, October 30, 1982; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 26)
    - Herman Mayer interview, Helena, Montana, August 24, 1983; Interview conducted in German and English. (Cassette Cassette 27)
    - Agatha Brackmann interview, Helena, Montana, August 24, 1983 (Cassette Cassette 27)
    - Reverend Larry LaDassor interview, Butte, Montana, August 17, 1983 (Cassette Cassette 28)
    - Dutch Cloke and Helen Peterson interview, Butte, Montana, August 17, 1983 (Cassette Cassette 28)
    - Hertha Ziegler and Margaret Bundschuh interview, Helena, Montana, August 31, 1983 (Cassette Cassette 29)
    - Margaret Maier interview, Missoula, Montana, February 24, 1984; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 30)
    - Josephine Stepanzoff interview and poetry reading, Missoula, Montana, March 3, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 31)
    - Clara Faul interview, Helena, Montana, August 21, 1984; Interview conducted in German. (Cassette Cassette 32)
    - Mabel Murphy interview, Wolf Creek, Montana, September 14, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 33)
    - Rose and Anna Busch interview, Butte, Montana, September 14, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 34)
    - Clarence Wendel interview, Missoula, Montana, September 1984 (Cassette Cassette 35)
    - Hans Luthje interview, Philipsburg, Montana, September 1984 (Cassette Cassette 35)
    - Arthur Seiler and Bernice Mitchell interview, October 1984 (Cassette Cassette 36)
    - Lawrence Wendel interview, Clancy, Montana, October 5, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 37)
    - Arthur Seiler, Jr. interview, Clancy, Montana, October 7, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 38)
    - Lawrence Wendel interview, Clancy, Montana, October 7, 1984 (Cassette Cassette 38)
    - Delilah Hert interview, Hardin, Montana, circa 1980 (Cassette Cassette 39)
    - Jakab "Jake" Lackmann interview, Hardin, Montana, circa 1980; Interview conducted in English and German. (Cassette Cassette 39)
    - Frieda Geary interview and music, circa 1980 (Cassette Cassette 40)
    - Gertrud Lackschewitz audio recording, 1981; Reading the story of St. Paul’s Mission. (Cassette Cassette 41)
    - Heidi W. Graham interview, Glasgow, Montana, 1981 (Cassette Cassette 41)
    - O.J. Wall audio recording, 1981; Reading his family history from a newspaper article. (Cassette Cassette 41)
    - Anna Marie Steinke Rice interview, Frazer, Montana, 1981 (Cassette Cassette 41)
    - Elizabeth Hehn interview, August 1981 (Cassette Cassette 42)
- Writings and Lectures, 1979-2006; Series II; 0.4 linear feet
  - Writings and Lectures, 1979-2006; Subseries 1; 0.3 linear feet
    - "Deutsche Einwanderer in Montana," "German Immigrants in Montana", 1979 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - "Islands of 16th Century Germany in Montana: The Hutterite Colonies", 1980-1982 and undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    - "History of German Immigrants to Montana," Lecture, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - "Overview of German Immigration to Montana", October, 1983 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - "Germans in Missoula", 1983 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - "The Helena Germans: Ethnic Influences in a Western Mining Town, 1880-1930", October, 1984 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - "German Background Churches in Montana as Mediators of Ethnic Heritage, 1885-1930", 1984 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Lecture Announcements and Agreements, 1984 and undated (Box-folder 4/17)
    - "German Immigrants in Montana as Reflected in a German Newspaper", undated (Box-folder 4/18)
    - "Missoula's Ethnic Groups," Lecture, undated (Box-folder 4/19)
    - "Russian-Germans", undated (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Memoirs, 1979-2006; Subseries 2; 0.1 linear feet
    - "Zwischen den Wassern: Lebenserinnerungen," "Between the Waters: Memoirs", 2006 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - "Über den Wassern", memoir, 2006; This copy of the memoir is printed from a scan made in 2017 from Gertrud Lackschewitz's personal copy. The original was returned to her. The contents may be the same as "Zwischen den Wassern." (Box-folder 4/22)
- Correspondence, 1976-2008; Series III; 0.2 linear feet
  - Correspondence, General, 1976-1982 (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Correspondence, German-American Tricentennial, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Correspondence, General, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Correspondence, Sarah Stahl of Gildford Colony, Montana, 1983-2008 and undated (Box-folder 5/3)
- German-American Tricentennial, 1982-1983; Series IV; 0.2 linear feet
  - Tricentennial Research, 1982-1983 and undated (Box-folder 5/4)
  - 300 Years of Germans in North America Calendar, 1983 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - German-American Tricentennial Events Planning and Promotion, 1983 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - German-American Tricentennial Exhibit from Fort Missoula, Exhibit Tags, 1983 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - German-American Tricentennial Newsletters and Events, 1983 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - German-American Tricentennial Publications, 1983 (Box-folder 5/9)
- Card Files, circa 1965-1985; Series V; 1.7 linear feet
  - German Immigration in Montana, undated (Box 12)
  - Interviews in Montana by Region - Oral History Index, undated (Box 13)
  - Germans in Montana - References, undated (Box 14)
- German Immigrants in the United States Research Files, 1839-1984; Series VI; 1.0 linear foot
  - Poetry and Songs in Russian-German Dialect, 1839-1942 and undated (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Friedrich Holz Correspondence, German Immigrant Soldier in the Civil War, 1863-1864 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Kober Family Correspondence, 1872-1958 and undated (Box-folder 5/12)
  - German Hymns and Prayer Books, Title Pages, 1890-1944 and undated (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Clippings, 1895-1984 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Hutterite Rechenschaft, 1902 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Fruchte deutscher Arbeit: Memoir of a German Immigrant in Idaho, 1910 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Apotheker-Zeitung, German Language Newspapers, 1913-1918 (Folder OS 16)
  - Political Propaganda, 1914-1918 and undated (Box-folder 5/17)
  - World War I, 1917-1918 and undated (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Hutterites, 1918-2007 and undated (Box-folder 6/2)